<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>API on Tanmay Chakrabarty</title><link>https://tanmaychk.github.io/tags/api/</link><description>Recent content in API on Tanmay Chakrabarty</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 18:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tanmaychk.github.io/tags/api/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Making sense of the news with GPT-3, NLTK, Python and Streamlit</title><link>https://tanmaychk.github.io/post/gpt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tanmaychk.github.io/post/gpt/</guid><description>&lt;p>ChatGPT buzz is all around and I was keen to use the GPT-3 API in a project. In this post I will walk through the process of creating a Python web app using Streamlit, called &amp;ldquo;News 📰 Sense.&amp;rdquo; The app fetches top news articles from the News API, generate summaries of each article using the OpenAI GPT-3 model, analyze the sentiment of the article using the Natural Language Toolkit (NLTK) library, and classifies the articles into different categories based on keywords.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="understanding-sentiment-analysis">Understanding Sentiment Analysis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sentiment analysis is a natural language processing (NLP) technique used to determine the sentiment or emotion expressed in a piece of text. It aims to understand whether the text conveys a positive, negative, or neutral sentiment. For my project I used the &lt;a href="https://www.nltk.org/_modules/nltk/sentiment/vader.html">VADER&lt;/a> (Valence Aware Dictionary and sEntiment Reasoner) lexicon from the NLTK library.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The VADER lexicon contains a list of words and their associated sentiment scores. It takes into account the intensity of the sentiment words and the context in which they appear to provide a compound sentiment score. A positive (pos) score indicates a positive sentiment, a negative (neg) score indicates a negative sentiment, and a score close to zero suggests a neutral (neu) sentiment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="categorizing-news-articles">Categorizing News Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Categorizing news articles helps in organizing and presenting information effectively. In my app, I classify each article into predefined categories, such as Business, Technology, Sports, Entertainment, Politics, and Society. To achieve this, I created a list of keywords associated with each category. In the code I checked if any of these keywords are present in the article content, and if so, assigned the article to the corresponding category.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="summarizing-news-articles-with-gpt-3">Summarizing News Articles with GPT-3&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Summarization is the process of condensing a longer piece of text into a shorter, concise version that captures the essential information. For summarizing news articles, I used the OpenAI &lt;a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/models/gpt-3">GPT-3 DaVinci&lt;/a>, a powerful language generation model that can generate human-like text. Shameless admission: Using GPT was the main draw for this project :)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>GPT-3 works by taking a prompt (the news article content in our case) and generating a continuation or summary based on that prompt. We specify the maximum number of tokens for the summary to control its length. The GPT-3 model is fine-tuned to understand context and generate coherent and contextually relevant summaries.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-application">The application&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You can find the code for News 📰 Sense and instructions to use it at &lt;a href="https://github.com/tanmaychk/News-Sense">https://github.com/tanmaychk/News-Sense&lt;/a>. Before starting, make sure you have the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Python installed on your system&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An API key from the News API. You can sign up and get your API key from &lt;a href="https://newsapi.org/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An API key from OpenAI GPT-3. You can obtain your API key from &lt;a href="https://platform.openai.com/account/api-keys">OpenAI&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-have-been-the-learnings">What have been the Learnings&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As a developer, this project allowed me to apply various NLP concepts and technologies in a practical and meaningful way:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>API Integration&lt;/strong>: how to integrate external APIs like the News API and OpenAI GPT-3 API into Python code to access real-time news data and perform advanced language generation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Natural Language Processing (NLP)&lt;/strong>: By utilizing the NLTK library, gained insights into how NLP techniques like sentiment analysis and tokenization work. I also understood how the VADER lexicon is used to determine the sentiment of text.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Machine Learning for Language Generation&lt;/strong>: experimented with OpenAI GPT-3, a state-of-the-art language model capable of generating human-like text. I utilized it to summarize news articles, demonstrating the power of machine learning in language tasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Text Classification&lt;/strong>: applied text classification to categorize news articles based on specific keywords. This demonstrated how NLP techniques can be used for content organization and user-friendly presentation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Streamlit Web App Development&lt;/strong>: I had used Streamlit earlier as well, in another project. Streamlit&amp;rsquo;s simplicity allows us to focus on functionality and visualization rather than dealing with web development complexities.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="further-steps">Further Steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The News Sense app can perhaps be further enhanced by incorporating user input for customized news filtering, improving summarization techniques, or integrating more advanced language models. I will implement them, when I get time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was a joy working on the project, hope you liked it as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Cross posted at &lt;a href="https://dev.to/tanmaychk/making-sense-of-the-news-with-gpt-python-and-streamlit-33c6">Dev.To&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item></channel></rss>